This is the first higher Ed hot
take, and boy is it a doozy.
I'm your host, Joel Goodman.
Here we are talking about ai.
Again, there's so much blind trust in
these products floating around higher
ed and I have felt the need to bring a
critical lens to assessing these things,
and I've been saying it a lot lately.
I'm a critic, not a skeptic, but from
here on out, I'm gonna be using the term
LLM because the way we use AI today is
purely as a marketing term, taken from
another technology and slapped onto
machine learning by Sam Altman and OpenAI.
What you use every day and call AI is.
Still just machine learning.
And we've had that for decades and it's
very useful, but doesn't sound as flash
when you decouple it from the chat.
Products you've been duped
into believing is ai.
Did you know that Open AI lost
$5 billion after revenue in 2024?
The company that owns chat, GPT
empowers most of the other products.
Your institution is probably paying five
or six figure sums for, lost $5 billion.
Even with all the revenue they bring
in from chat, GPT subscriptions
and API contracts, according to
financial reporting, it costs
OpenAI $1 billion more than all of
its revenue to run its software.
That's a problem.
OpenAI loses money on
every call to its API.
Every question you ask chat, GPT, and
every run of a custom GPT that you make.
And worse still, they lose more money
the more customers they acquire.
This is not a sustainable business.
And, uh, the same is true for
Anthropic the company behind Claude.
That means that the price you're
paying for LLM powered software is well
below the cost it takes to actually
run it somewhere around 125% less
than the actual cost to run them.
These products have been backed
by venture capital based on
little more than smoke and mirrors
With news that Microsoft is pulling back
on the very data center, build outs that
power most of open AI's GPTs, there's
a very real chance that this bubble
we've been ignoring is about to burst.
If I could generalize a bit, there
are two kinds of AI thought leaders
and only one gets listened to First.
There's the evangelist who knows
enough about how to use these.
Systems and the general framework
for how the models are constructed.
The evangelists are all in
either because they're super
optimistic or super opportunistic.
Either they're happy to ignore
all the warning signs and continue
hyping chat GPT as a solution.
Despite the very real possibility.
Reality will catch up with them,
or they see the potential for a
short-term cash return and are
pretty cynical about society.
If they can get rich off of your
lack of knowledge, they will.
AI evangelists fall into two camps.
They're the ones who started or shifted
their businesses to taking advantage
of this new wave of LLM dominance.
They built chat interfaces, CRMs code,
and search front ends that are wrapped
around open AI or philanthropic.
They feed your data back to
these companies and then pin
their business to this bubble.
They don't actually own the tech.
They rent GPU cycles and
create marketing buzz.
Then they're the so-called experts
who played with the early chat
GPT web app and saw an opportunity
to own a thought leadership lane.
You've seen them at conferences
trying to help you figure out how
to use LLMs in your own workflows.
We've all learned a ton from them.
Maybe they've written a
book about AI already.
They are genuinely trying to
help us stay ahead of the curve.
Then there's AI critics, and this is me.
I've been using these tools longer
than most of the evangelists.
I'm always an early adopter
and I'm always critical.
When I lived in Austin and was plugged
into the startup scene, I used to tell
people I'd be a terrible VC because
I thought everyone's ideas were bad.
I'm a critic and I do keep a watchful eye.
Critics aren't skeptical though.
We count data scientists, machine learning
engineers, marketers, journalists,
and plenty of others among our rinks.
We don't believe the hype, but
we test it against reality.
If the bubble is about to burst,
we need to sound the alarm.
So onto the problem first.
Do you really think that chatting
with a computer is a good
experience and like super useful
as a general everyday activity?
Like the most efficient way to interact
with LMS is to spend brain power trying
to figure out how to prompt it best and
physically typing that into a chat box.
We've done that before y'all.
It's called programming and it's why
we have graphical user interfaces
because it's faster to use an interface.
Like, I get it for doing deep
research, but the chat part of
chat GPT is not the product.
In fact, LLM shouldn't be the product,
even though they're sold like they are.
LLM should be part of the infrastructure,
making products better and the best.
All of these supposedly brilliant
people can come up with is chat.
Get real.
Come on.
I mean, really
meanwhile, university websites are still
slow and institutions are adding more AI
chat bot and search and RFI forms that
pop up at supposedly just the right time.
It's, it's just junk.
It's just junk that slows down
our website and makes them worse
to use while search engines are
eating our traffic for breakfast.
You've seen those AI summaries, right?
People aren't getting to your websites
anymore and you're making them heavier
and making it harder so that the ones
that even get there don't use them.
What are we doing seriously?
How is any of this strategic?
Your strategy is to skip past
doing the actual work and expect
half-baked, consistently hallucinating
predictive algorithms to make
everything better, seriously.
This is me saying it louder for everyone.
AI tools are not a replacement
for content strategy.
They're not a replacement for UX design.
They're not a replacement
for brand strategy.
AI tools are not a replacement for
admissions counselors and they're
not a replacement for human kindness.
But we're still out here paying lip
service to the actions we know we
should be taking while dumping cash.
We don't have into middleware.
That ruins the environment, guts
the arts, and steals from the
very people that we educate.
How do you square that with the
mission of higher education?
So why are you spending money on chatbots
and targeted ad style contact forms?
Why are you giving money to a company
that will either fail bringing an entire
industry down with it, or raise its prices
so high you'll never be able to recover?
I'm begging you to pause and think
bigger about LLMs, think bigger
about what value they have, but
also think more sustainably.
What I've taken away from
this AI craze is this.
The billions and billions of dollars
set on fire by these companies and
the possibly irreparable damage to
the planet that they've done have
brought the promise of big data
analysis to our personal computers.
And when you clear past the hype
and marketing and evangelists,
this is an incremental gain.
the biggest advance is that every
institution now has the power to
analyze all of its data, find trends,
do market analysis, and reduce the
workload of its already overworked staff.
The bloated, expensive operational
side of running a college or university
can be made more efficient, freeing
up the messy humanity needed side of
the house to provide better care to
your prospective students and donors.
You know what doesn't do that?
Chat bots, especially ones
that give the wrong answers.
Site search that nobody uses.
6% of your traffic and most
of that's internal and hard.
Cells that cover up broken ux.
There are other ways.
There are smarter, more effective
ways to implement this stuff.
And right now, can you really
afford to be betting the house on
someone else's failing business?